in this video we're going to be
continuing on with our weather
derivative series and specifically
looking at ways that we can actually
model the temperature volatility now we
have a modified ulnstein erlenbeck
process
that we've actually defined the
parameters for in previous videos and
now we're trying to specify models for
our time varying volatility parameter
now if you can remember from last time
using our model we created this
simulation
across a number of periods where t is
our real temperature and then this line
yellow line is the model so our model is
now capturing those average temperatures
um throughout the periods however we
need to capture
that difference in volatility between
seasons
so we have a number of ways of doing
that we have
piecewise constant functions so this is
where we can try and capture the
volatility for each specific season say
months we've got parametric regression
polynomial we've got non-parametric
regression like splines we've got
fourier series to model the volatility
of temperature and we've got stochastic
differential equations
so
let's get into it and we'll first look
at the piecewise constant functions just
a reminder that we've got temperature
data going all the way back to 1860 all
the way through to today for sydney so
what we can do is we can get the
unbiased estimator
for the quadratic variation of this
temperature process and that's just
going to be the standard deviation of
this process so i've done this for each
day and that's the line in blue i've
then shown with reference of the mean
temperature what the percentage
volatility is here in orange and as you
can see as we progress throughout the
year
this value has changed so what we really
want is we want models to try and
given a day in the year or a specific
period we want to be able to model this
volatility this standard deviation that
we have in blue again our summary of our
modified um einstein ulembek process is
that we've got this modified
dynamics here where we've defined the
mean reversion parameter we have our
change in daily average temperature
t bar and then we've got the first
derivative which is captured here hence
the modified ou dynamics now we want to
actually define what this volatility
parameter sigma
that's varying with time is
so the volatility of the temperature
process like i've just said
the estimator is based on the quadratic
variation of this temperature process
and that's our our best estimate is uh
the standard deviation or the biased
standard deviation of this process so
our volatility is a dynamic volatility
of this temperature process and this
could be seasonal daily monthly etc
so if we first take a look and we just
group on the day again we get that blue
line and i've just plotted standard
deviation on the left hand side with
days
366 to include the leap years there
now
let's look at the first method for
modeling this so we've got piecewise
constant functions so what i'm going to
do here is i'm going to come up with two
data frames so i'm going to group on day
and get the standard deviation and i'm
going to group on month and get the
standard deviation i'm then going to add
these two data frames together and plot
that in a row and here you can see that
in
the orange i have that standard
deviation
for all the days
over our time period from 1860
all the way through to today and then
we've got the standard deviation of
the different periods in terms of months
so january february march etc and that's
there in blue
so as you can see this is what you would
call a piecewise constant function we
could fit this and make it non-constant
but i left this as the simplest option
for now we are capturing that
seasonality
that volatility
has for temperature
now parametric regression we have a
number of options but here we're going
to look at fitting polynomials for this
i'm going to be using the stats models
api and then sky learn pre-processing
polynomial features
so here what i'm going to do is i'm
going to set and initialize my degrees
of freedom i'm going to go and test
polynomials with order 3 to 7 i'm going
to fit my our transform our original
data
and then i'm going to fit using ordinary
least squares
once i've done that i can predict using
my original data and fit the model and
i'll show you the plots here so by
looking at this graph we can actually
see that there are some models that have
been very overfitted and some that have
potentially underfitted underfitted for
example the three degree model in red
doesn't really capture some of these
dynamics during the low points in the
season and doesn't capture this high
point
in the season during summer whereas
we've got some overfitting here with the
higher degree polynomials maybe six and
seven where we're completely
misrepresenting the first part of the
year
so
how are we going to get the best fit
in a personal way and what i mean by
that is with the least number of degrees
of freedom well we can use the aka
information criterion the aic criterion
to judge the tarsonomy between model fit
and complexity
so all i need to do is that because i've
used the
ols module using the stats models i can
just print out um the aic criterion and
of course we want to go for the lowest
aic
which is parsonamous so here i'm going
to pick um the order the fifth order
polynomial and obviously in the graph we
can see that that fits quite well if we
then print that out more explicitly you
can see that here's our polynomial fit
with five fifth order polynomial in the
red and that fits our volatility nicely
now let's take a look at another
methodology and this is the local and
non-parametric regression so here we can
use spline so interpolation is a method
of estimating unknown data points in a
given range spline interpolation is a
type of piecewise polynomial
interpolation method so spline
interpolation is a useful method in
smoothing the curve of surface data now
a b spline curve fitting specifically or
basis spline is a curve approximation
method that requires parameters such as
knots spline coefficients and degree of
the spline so to construct a smoother
spline fit we need to specify the number
of knots and this is the number of knots
within our given data set that we're
actually defining um to smooth out our
curve so knots are the joints on the
polynomial segments and we get to define
the number of them that they are so the
steps in b-spline curve fitting is that
based on the knots number that we define
we'll determine the new x-data vector by
using the quantile function
then we'll be using the spl rep function
and it returns a tuple containing the
vector of you guessed it the parameters
that we need not spline coefficients and
the degree of the spline
so then we're going to use the b spline
class to construct spline fit on this x
vector data
so from scipy we're going to import
interpolate and we're going to use our
data of
the temperature volatility and the
standard deviation over those
days in the year
we're going to first off just to find
the not number as 5 to show you how this
works we're then going to find the new
quartile representation of this number
and then we're going to pass that
through into our spl rep function in sci
pi interpolate that gives us back the
tuple of which we get the not number
we get the coefficients and then we get
the degrees
of complexity of the b-spline so then
now we can fit this b-spline model using
that tuple
that we've just said with our original
data set and what you get is
essentially a spline fit as we have here
in red so this is with a five number of
knots but what happens when we want to
test different number of knots aka
adding complexity to our model well now
i can define a spline function when
i've actually defined my number of knots
the reason that we have plus two here is
because you always have two knots at the
start and the end of your data series
so here we've um just getting our y fit
for each different interpolation with
the number of knots given so here the
number of knots i'm testing is 3 10 20
30 50 and 80 and i'm going to plot those
out now the other number i've plotted
here is the residual sum of squares the
mean squared error
which here is really an indicative of
fit and although this rss goes down as
we increase the complexity and knots
what you can see is an incredible amount
of overfitting as we start getting down
to
well up to a number of 80. so you can
see an incredible amount of overfitting
to reduce that rss
whereas we're looking for something
quite parsonamous
so
really you you could be using some kind
of metric to to judge palsonomy with the
number of knots being like a number a
parameter and you could use that as a
penalty and then you could use rrs as a
measure of fit you could define any any
uh equation you want to try and find a
pass on this model but in this case i
might go
with number with 10 knots and i think
that looks like a good fit even three
has done as good a job as our polynomial
nearly now let's explore using fourier
series to model the volatility of
temperature so here a fourier series
we've got these coefficients in front of
our cosine and sine functions and the
cos and sine functions have different
orders of magnitude and really it's
can be an infinite sum but we're
actually going to sum up a case i here
and that defines the order of the
fourier series so here we've got the sum
of all these cosine functions and sine
functions and we want to estimate the
parameters that give the best fit to our
model so first off what we're going to
do is we're going to look at long-term
volatility so here i'm going to take the
rolling 30-day standard deviation so
that means that we get a standard
deviation for every 30 for every day but
it's the rolling 30 day standard
deviation
so
here i can see that we have
quite a solid mean that's really
centered around our data
so i'm quite happy with using a fourier
series just off of this
with no linear trend
if there was a linear trend here present
in volatility
then i could add that here
instead of just having a coefficient for
my volatility out the front of my
fourier series
now the way i'm going to test different
fourier series and try and fit by least
squares is i'm going to use this sim fit
module in python that's been written so
pip install sim fit go look at the
documentation but essentially what we
can do is we can pass a dictionary of
symbolic fourier series and what i mean
by that is that we can create a
dictionary and i've printed out one here
where we have our coefficients that
we're interested in and the particular
model that's passed through for
optimization now here this is a
third order model so i've passed in
a third order i've defined my frequency
because we know that the data is the
frequency is yearly we've experienced
that in our temperature so i'm happy to
then
redefine that frequency here again
so that's 2 times pi
divided by the
365.25 days and remember because we're
dealing with such a large amount of data
number of years
we have to account for that extra day in
year leap years what we're going to do
is we're going to test fourier orders
all the way from 1 3 to 10
using the range function and we're going
to look at the residual sum of squares
and what we can see is that the residual
sum of squares really decreases until
about order 3 but even even we get
slight performance increase as we go to
6. so here i've just used the model 6
and then we've i've fit the parameters
using this
sim fit module and then what i can do is
i can print out the fourier series that
have resulted in the best fit and i
believe it uses least squares to find
these parameters
what that looks like essentially i've
just plotted the last
20 something years worth of data 25
years worth of data and you can see here
that we've got that black line which is
our fourier series composition
fifth order fourier series that we've
then repeated every year to try and
capture that volatility and if we look
at that more granularly just at a one
year basis we've essentially got this
blue line that's replicated from year to
year in our fourier series now this is
quite handy because the way that this
works is that i can take time actually
as the ordinal number starting from the
first ordinal number the same way we
have for our temperature series defined
so this is a quite handy way where we
can use the same indexing in terms of
time
for both defining the volatility and
then our temperature stochastic model
that we had from previous videos so i
i'm really liking this version so far
now last but not least we have
stochastic differential equation now
what i mean by that is we originally had
this modified einstein ulembek process
and
that's of this form here but now i
actually want to define
our volatility or the change in
volatility by nearly the same equation
i'm going to take that einstein ulembek
process and we're going to start
defining parameters now the handy thing
about this is that
we've already discovered that this long
term volatility
isn't time varying so really
if i
sorry the big change here is that i'm
going to chop up this data now and look
at standard deviation on a
month-to-month basis
so
just like with our
constant
piecewise function that was on a
month-to-month basis now i'm looking at
monthly volatility
so if we aggregate on the months
of our observed daily average
temperature we get this standard
deviation path and i've just reindexed
the time periods there zero bean from
january
1959 i think oh 1859 sorry so we've got
this average
standard deviation and that means that
this parameter here in our sde is not
going to be time varying now that is a
hidden gem because what it means is that
we can actually create our modified
ulnstein ulembek process like we had
before where we used the derivative of
our variable of interest our time
variant parameter and that means that
we'll be able to use the same
methodology to estimate our rate of mean
reversion as we did in the previous
video now we were able to auto regress
on our uh
our temperature parameter to then our
residual of the temperature parameter to
find this rate of mean reversion and
here we're going to be doing the same
thing with our volatility term to find
our rate of mean reversion but before
then we need to find this fixed
parameter that isn't going to be moving
with time we're going to set it as
as the overall process the volatility of
volatility
so of course the unbiased estimate
of volatility is going to be the same
for the quadratic variation process
so here we're going to take our standard
deviations
and we're going to get the standard
deviation of the temperature standard
deviation which sounds funny but
that's what we're going to define it as
that parameter that we're estimating is
gamma in our model so i've said that
gamma is
0.58 and it's remember it's important to
understand that time is now on a monthly
frequency in this sub sde so just like
the previous
video we are actually going to calculate
this rate of mean reversion
by using a lag process we can do that
because
the modified dynamics is no different to
this dynamics because the change of our
our average volatility over time is
actually it's it's it's constant so it's
equal to zero so we can just add that
term in and then we can use the lag of
the volatility process to calculate our
uh our rate of remain reversion if you
don't know what i'm talking about please
go ahead and look at the video last week
i'll put a link to it here so i'm going
to use our autoregressive model and
we're going to be passing our data so
our volatility standard deviation
and we're going to have a one lag term
so we've got an auto regressive model
with one lag term we're going to fit
that and then we're going to look at the
fit and then the parameter and the rate
of mean reversion of the volatility
process that we get is
0.954 or thereabouts so now the
stochastic differential equation that
we've completed is of this form here
now in order to simulate this specific
path we would use a euler scheme
approximation for each month this
volatility uh would be simulated as per
this sde
and then we would use that monthly
volatility for a whole month
of temperature simulations for each day
within that month and then you would
progress from month to month
now
the reason that i've done this on a
monthly basis is just to show you a bit
of variety
of this model compared to another model
where we might be able to get volatility
per day in quite a um
well a parametric way where we just feed
in the the time and then we're going to
get a volatility back that's fixed now
it's important to note that we could
actually fit a stochastic differential
equation of this form for each
individual month
um that would be a bit overkill for this
exercise but it could be done again you
can vary your frequency of time that you
want to assess these periods over
as as you wish but hopefully that's
given you five different ways that you
can actually model volatility and then
incorporate that within your modified
ornstein ulembek process
for temperature dynamics
next episode we're going to be using all
these dynamics in our fitted temperature
volatility models to be able to price
weather derivatives in full so stay
tuned for that until next time youtube
see you later
[Music]
you